Mss.913.748.Un3
American Philosophical Society
United States. Work Projects Administration (Pa.) Reports, 1918-1948
Mss.913.748.Un3
American Philosophical Society
0.25 Linear feet 38 items.
These are site reports on archaeological excavations in northern and western Pennsylvania and upstate New York. Most of the excavations were sponsored by the Pennsylvania Historical Commission (1929-1948). The reports include photographs, maps, and diagrams.
38 items.
United States.Work Projects Administration (Pa.)
Box 1
Scope and Contents note
A series of manuscripts, reports, maps, and photographs on Pennsylvania archeology from the Pennsylvania Historical and Museum Commission files. Many of these reports are records of Works Progress Administration Archeological Projects in Pennsylvania, but more than half represent activities of the State Commission. Primarily excavations of Native American burial mounds in northern and western Pennsylvania, with some upstate New York sites. 38 items, plus Edmund S. Carpenter’s summary of data on Pennsylvania tumuli entitled “The ancient mounds of Pennsylvania.” (913.748 C223)
Scope and Contents note
Native American Images note: Almost 2,000 black and white silver gelatin photographs, black and white negatives, ink and pencil sketches, maps, blueprints, and graphs of Seneca and other Iroquoian burial mounds excavated in conjunction with the Pennsylvania Historical Commission and the WPA from 1918-1948. The tumulus are located in northern, western, and central Pennsylvania, particularly Warren County’s Cornplanter tract, with some mounds unearthed in western Cattaraugus and Chautauqua counties of New York. Images include excavation sites with marked trenches; artifacts of tools, pottery, arrow points, and pipes; skeletal remains in burial vaults; Seneca workers; and diagrams of archeological finds. Referenced in Freeman’s Guide to manuscripts relating to the American Indian and Supplement, David Van Keuren’s The Proper Study of Mankind, an annotated bibliography of manuscript sources on anthropology and archeology, and Murphy Smith’s Historical American Sketches.
Maps note: There are approximately 50 maps in this collection.
Related Archival Materials note
Summarized in Edmund S. Carpenter, Ancient Mounds of Pennsylvania (913.748 C223).
Immediate Source of Acquisition note
Presented by Edmund S. Carpenter and accessioned, 1948-1949.
Other Finding Aids note
Freeman guide, #180. Realms of Gold, #49.
Bird, Junius Bouton, 1907-; Biss, Wesley L.; Butler, Mary; Cadzow, Donald A.; Carpenter, Edmund, 1922-2011; Cresson, Francis C.; Fisher, G. S.; Gerrodette, F.; Gilmore, Raymond M., (Raymond Maurice), 1907-1983; Jones, Robert W.; Pennsylvania Historical Commission.; Schoff, Harry L.; Skinner, Dorothy P.; Smith, Charles M.; Stewart, T. D., (Thomas Dale), 1901-; Thomas, Cyrus; Witthoft, John; Wright, Ross P.; Archaeology; Blueprints.; Diagrams.; Eastern Woodlands Indians; Excavations (Archaeology); Gelatin silver prints; Graphs.; Human remains (Archaeology); Indians of North America--New York (State)--Antiquities; Indians of North America--Pennsylvania--Antiquities; Iroquois Indians--Antiquities; Maps.; Negatives; New York (State) -- Antiquities.; Pennsylvania -- Antiquities.; Photomechanical prints; Photoprints.; Seneca Indians--Antiquities; Seneca Indians--Implements; Sketches.
- McFate site report on archaeological excavations, Crawford County, Pennsylvania, 1938; No.1; Schoff, Harry L.
  Scope and Contents note
  Native American Images note: 49 black and white photographs of excavation of a prehistoric Indian village. Images include landscapes, trenches, skeletal remains, arrowpoints, pipes, pottery, tools.
  Other Finding Aids note
  Freeman guide, #2694
- Site report: summary of lists for Somerset and Fayette Counties, Pennsylvania, 1941; No.2; Cresson, Francis C.
  Native American Images note: 22 pencil sketches of skeletal remains and diagrams of excavation sites with location of finds.
  Freeman guide, #2674
- Identification of faunal remains from Southwestern Pennsylvania, archaeological sites and reports of animal remains, 1941; No.3; Gilmore, Raymond M., (Raymond Maurice), 1907-1983
  Freeman guide, #2688
- Skeletal remains from Fayette and Somerset County, Pennsylvania, 1944; No.4; Stewart, T. D., (Thomas Dale), 1901-
  Native American Images note: 5 black and white photographs of skeletal remains dated ca. 1550-1650.
  Freeman guide, #2698
- Archaeological survey of Somerset County, Pennsylvania, 1941-1942; No.5; Cresson, Francis C.
  Freeman guide, #2684
- Materials relating to Brock Mound, Lycoming County, Pennsylvania, 1947; No.6, part 1; Carpenter, Edmund, 1922-2011
  Native American Images note: 1 pencil sketch of the excavation site at Brock Mound.
  Freeman guide, #2678
- Materials relating to Brock Mound, Lycoming County, Pennsylvania, 1947; No.6, part 2; Carpenter, Edmund, 1922-2011
  Native American Images note: 23 black and white photographs of artifacts found at the excavation site. Images include fragments of tools, pipes, pottery, arrow points, and diagrams of the site.
- Record of excavation of Brock village site, Lycoming County, Pennsylvania, 1937; No.7; Schoff, Harry L.
  Native American Images note: 4 black and white photographs, 1 ink sketch of tools, pottery fragments, plan of the Algonquin site, Muncy Creek township.
  Freeman guide, #2696
- Miscellaneous reports on Johnson, Miller, Jacobs, Hook Run, Logan, Jimerson sites, 1941; No.8; Butler, Mary
  Native American Images note: 117 black and white photographs, 44 black and white negatives of mounds, excavation sites, Seneca masks, artifact fragments from the Cornplanter reservation, Warren County, Pennsylvania; Cattaraugus County, New York; Scandia, Pennsylvania and others.
  Freeman guide, #2673
  - Johnson Halftown, 1941
  - Seneca excavation site, 1941
  - Seneca excavation site, 1941
- Irvine Mound group materials, Warren County, Pennsylvania, 1937; No.9a, part 1; Cadzow, Donald A.; Schoff, Harry L.
  Native American Images note: 19 black and white photographs, 50 black and white negatives of landscapes, excavation trenches, skeletal remains, tools, burial vaults at three ancient mounds at Irvine.
  Freeman guide, #3238
- Irvine Mound group materials, Warren County, Pennsylvania, 1937; No.9a, part 2; Cadzow, Donald A.; Schoff, Harry L.
  Native American Images note: 5 ink sketches of diagrams of excavation sites of Irvine mound, Warren County, Pennsylvania and Nelson mound, Crawford County, Pennsylvania.
- Irvine Mound group materials, Warren County, Pennsylvania, 1937; No.9b; Cadzow, Donald A.; Schoff, Harry L.
  Native American Images note: 3 ink sketches of diagrams of excavation sites; 25 black and white photographs of tools, arrowpoints, and plans of burial mounds.
- Irvine Mound group materials, Warren County, Pennsylvania, 1937; No.9c; Cadzow, Donald A.; Schoff, Harry L.
  Native American Images note: 24 black and white photographs, 20 black and white negatives, 6 sketches of diagrams of the excavation of Nathaniel Mound. Images include landscapes, excavation trenches, burial sites, arrowpoints,
- Nelson Mound materials, 1938?; No.10; Schoff, Harry L.
  Native American Images note: 2 black and white photographs, 4 maps of a small burial mound, diagrams and sketches of the central grave in Crawford County, Pennsylvania.
  Freeman guide, #2695
- Book Mound materials, 1929; No.11; Jones, Robert W.
  Native American Images note: 2 black and white photographs of mound in Beale township, Juniata County, Pennsylvania.
  Freeman guide, #2689
- Archaeological explorations in Western Pennsylvania, 1930-1935; No.12; Cadzow, Donald A.
  Native American Images note: 15 photomechanical prints of photographs and sketches of pottery, excavation sites, and diagrams of finds at 28th Street site, Erie, Pennsylvania.
  Freemna guide, #2675
- Letters to Cyrus Thomas, 1886; No.13; Smith, Charles M.
  Freeman guide, #2697
- Spartansburg Mound materials, 1934-1941; No.14; Freeman guide, #2679; Carpenter, Edmund, 1922-2011
  Native American Images note: 24 black and white photographs, 5 black and white negatives, 17 ink sketches, 2 geological maps of the mound including images of artifacts, arrowheads, burial sites, tools, diagrams, and workers.
- Alleghany Valley materials, 1941; No.15; Carpenter, Edmund, 1922-2011
  Native American Images note: 4 black and white photographs, 2 black and white negatives, 8 pencil sketches of excavations sites in Warren, Forest and Erie Counties.
  Freeman guide, #2676
- Darlington Mound report, 1918; No.16
  Native American Images note: 1 black and white photograph, 1 ink sketch of skeletal remains, diagram of site finds at Guyasutha mound, Allegheny County, Pennsylvania.
  Freeman guide, #2686
- Williams Mound report, 1941; No.17; Biss, Wesley L.
  Native American Images note: 41 black and white photographs, 20 black and white negatives, 2 sketches of excavation trenches, diagrams of site near Croydon, Warren County, Pennsylvania.
  Freeman guide, #2702
- A report...upon Clemson's Mound, 1929?; No.18; Jones, Robert W.
  Native American Images note: 22 ink sketches of plans and finds at the excavation site on an island in the Susquehanna River, Dauphin County, Pennsylvania.
  Freeman guide, #2690
- McKees Rock materials, 1939; No.19a, part 1; Gerrodette, F.
  Freeman guide, #2691
- McKees Rock materials, 1939; No.19a, part 2; Gerrodette, F.
  Native American Images note: 8 black and white photographs, 7 sketches of artifacts found including images of arrowheads, tools, skeletal remains, pottery, and maps and diagrams of finds.
- McKees Rock materials, 1939; No.19b; Gerrodette, F.
- Skeletal remains from the Sugar Run Mounds, 1945; No.20; Stewart, T. D., (Thomas Dale), 1901-
  Native American Images note: 2 black and white photographs of skulls found at site in Warren County, Pennsylvania.
  Freeman guide, #2699
- Sugar Run materials, 1940; No.21a
  Native American Images note: 107 black and white photographs, 34 black and white negatives of excavation sites of Northwest Pennsylvania. Images include excavation sites, skeletal reamins, tools, Seneca Indian workers.
  Freeman guide, #2700
- Sugar Run materials, 1940; No.21b
  Native American Images note: 95 black and white photographs, 28 negatives of aerial views of the Alleghany Valley; near Kinzua, Pennsylvania; Cornplanter reservation; a fort near Pittsfield.
- Sugar Run materials, 1940; No.21c
  Native American Images note: 196 black and white photographs, 57 black and white negatives of excavation sites in Warren County, Pennsylvania. Images include fire hearths, burial sites, tools, arrowpoints, pottery, pipes, skeletal remains, Seneca Indian workers.
- Sugar Run materials, 1940; No.21d
  Native American Images note: 149 black and white photographs, 50 black and white negatives of excavations and mounds in Warren County, Pennsylvania. Images include mound construction, excavation trenches, cremation hearth, and Seneca Indian workers.
- Southwest Pennsylvania materials, 1937-1939; No.22; Fisher, G. S.
  Native American Images note: 4 pencil sketches of diagrams of site finds, maps, Indian figure.
  Freeman guide, #2687
- Reports, 1931-1934; No.23; Schoff, Harry L.
  Native American Images note: 35 black and white photographs, 9 sketches of Wheatland mound, Kip Island site, Eagle Bluff site in Seneca County, New York. Images include arrowpoints, tools, pipes, maps and diagrams of site finds.
  Freeman guide, #1226
- Vandalia Mound materials, 1941; No.24
  Native American Images note: 1 black and white photograph, 6 sketches of tools and diagrams of site in Cattaraugus County, New York.
  Freeman guide, #1241
- Materials on the 28th Street site and Wesleyville site, Erie County, Pennsylvania, 1934; No.25; Carpenter, Edmund, 1922-2011
  Native American Images note: 96 black and white photographs, 15 sketches of tools, skeletal remains, landscapes, excavation sites, jewelry, arrowpoints, pottery, pipes, Seneca Indian workers. Also, diagrams of Fort Hill, Gower, Recker, Peck, Troutman, Emerick, Powell, Martin, Phillips sites.
  Freeman guide, #2680
- Reports of Pennsylvania Archaeological survey, 1929; No.26; Skinner, Dorothy P.
  Native American Images note: 1 geological map, 5 ink sketches of rock shelter at Miller township, Perry County, Pennsylvania.
  Freeman guide, #3239
- Profiles of Sugar Run sites, 1939-1941; No.27
  Freeman guide, #2693
- Photographs of sites and artifacts of Fort Hill, Martin, Phillips, and other locations, 1941; No.28; Cresson, Francis C.
  Native American Images note: 60 black and white photographs, 27 negatives, 15 sketches, 6 photomechanical prints of excavation sites, skeletal remains, pottery, tools, pipes, and aerial views of the Southwest Pennsylvania woodlands excavation sites.
  Freeman guide, #2685
  - Iroquois artifacts, 1941; Cresson, Francis C.
  - Iroquois effigy pipe, 1941; Pfirman, Kenneth R.
  - Iroquois excavation site, 1934; Woodruff, D. E.
  - Iroquois pottery, 1934; Cadzow, Donald A.
- Field drawings from the Sick site, South Towanda, Bradford County, Pennsylvania, 1948; No.29; Witthoft, John, 1921-
  Native American Images note: 1 ink sketch, 51 bluprints of locations of skeletal remains.
  Freeman guide, #2703